The All-Knowing
（水月）これが…　初代火影？
That's the First Hokage?
（水月）
忍の神と謳われた柱間の本物か。
The real Hashirama who's been
touted as a God of Shinobi?
（扉間）また大蛇丸とかいう忍か。
Don't tell me it's that
shinobi Orochimaru again!
（柱間）どういうことだ？
What do you mean?
（ヒルゼン）我々を封印していた
屍鬼封尽の術。
I suspect he undid
the Reaper Deal
おそらく
それを解いたのでしょう。
that has been keeping us
sealed away.
そして　その後　穢土転生を。
And then performed
the Reanimation Jutsu.
（ミナト）
まさか　あの封印術を解くなんて。
No way...
You found out how to undo
that Sealing Jutsu?
大蛇丸さん　どうやって？
How did you do
that Mr. Orochimaru?
（大蛇丸）私をみくびりすぎよ　ミナト。
You underestimate me, Minato.
うずまき一族の封印術→
Originally a Sealing Jutsu
of the Uzumaki Clan...
今はなき一族の跡地や→
I've been researching the ruins
and scattered documents
散らばってしまった文献を
ずっと研究してたのよ。
of the now extinct clan
ever since I lost my jutsu.
術を失ってからね。
初代様　どうやら我々は→
Lord First...
It appears we've been recalled
into the world of the living.
この世に再び
よみがえったようです。
ヌッ！　貴様は誰ぞ？
Who the hell are you?!
あ…　えぇ。
Oh, uh...
四代目火影です。
The Fourth Hokage, sir.
ほぉ　四代目とな！　そうか　うむ。
Oh? The Fourth Hokage,
you say?
I see!
里も安定しておるようだな。
So the village has
remained stable!
あの　安定しているかどうかは
私もよくわかりません。
Well, I'm not actually sure
if it has or not.
なんせ私は三代目より先に死んで
封印されてましたから。
Because I died and was sealed away
much earlier than Lord Third.
ぬ！　そうであったか。
Huh? Is that so...
猿飛と一緒に封印されたのとは
別件でか？
In a separate incident than when
I was sealed away with Sarutobi?
はい。　別の事件で…。
Yes...
a completely separate incident.
して　五代目は誰ぞ？
So who's the Fifth Hokage?
Your granddaughter,
Princess Tsunade.
お孫様の綱手姫ですよ。
綱か…。
Tsuna, huh?
今　里は大丈夫ぞ？
な　なにか心配でも？
Is the village okay?
Is there something to be
worried about?
初孫だったんで
果てしなく甘やかした。
She was my first grandchild,
so I spoiled her rotten!
しまいには　俺の賭け事まで覚えて
それはもう…。
In the end, she even picked up
my gambling habit...
（２人）ガハハッ。
《忍の神
想像してたのと少し違うな。
He's not what I expected
of someone considered to be
the God of Shinobi!
なんか…　う～ん》
How do I put it?
また穢土転生の術か。
The Reanimation Jutsu again...
わしの作った術をこうやすやすと。
I can't believe the jutsu I devised
would be used so casually.
それほど難しい術では
ありませんよ。
It's not a complex jutsu.
ただ作るべき術ではなかった。
However, you should not have
created it in the first place.
二代目　あなたのしてきた政策や
作った術が→
Lord Second...
Many of your policies and jutsu
that you developed
後々　厄介なことに
なってばかりでしてね。
ended up causing problems
later on down the line.
今回も。
貴様　また木ノ葉を襲う気か？
Even now...
Why you!
Are you planning on attacking
the Leaf again?!
わしの命と引きかえにしてまで
お前の術を奪ったというのに。
I took away your jutsu
in exchange for my own life.
なんたることじゃ！
Yet you still--!
今度は師であったわしまで
穢土転生して→
And this time you revived me,
your former master,
木ノ葉に仇なす気じゃな。
to pit me against the Leaf!
はぁ　いつの世も戦いか。
Conflict, no matter what the era.
確かに
あまりいい術とは言えぬな。
It certainly cannot be called
that great a jutsu.
扉間よ　だからあのとき
俺が言ったように…。
Tobirama, that's why I told you
that time to...
兄者は少し黙っていろ。
わしはこの若僧と話している。
Will you be quiet, big brother?
I am trying to talk to
this stripling right now.
しかしだの…。
黙れ！
But I...
Shut up!
《忍の神　貫禄ねえ～》
So not dignified for
the God of Shinobi!
勘違いしないでください。
Please do not misunderstand.
I don't have any more leanings
in that direction.
私はもうそんなことを
する気はありませんよ。
だから人格も縛ったり
してないでしょう？
Haven't you noticed that I'm not
suppressing your personalities?
今日は少し事情がありましてね
彼のたっての希望で→
There are certain circumstances
at play this time.
I'm merely creating a stage for
discourse per his strong desire.
話し合いの場を設けたまでです。
（サスケ）俺は　うちはサスケ。
I'm Sasuke Uchiha and I want to
ask you Hokage some things.
あんたたち火影に
聞きたいことがある。
サスケか。
Is that you Sasuke?
うちはの者か　なるほど。
悪党につくだけはある。
You belong to the Uchiha?
Of course you'd stick with
a scoundrel.
扉間　そういう言い方は
よせと言ったはずだぞ。
Tobirama! I told you to stop
saying such things!
兄者は甘いのだ！
You're too soft, big brother!
俺のことはいい。　三代目→
Never mind me.
Lord Third...
イタチに　なぜあんなことを？
Why did you make Itachi
do what he did?
もう知っておるようじゃな。
So, you've learned of
what happened.
イタチは　うちは一族の復讐として
俺が殺した。
I...killed Itachi to avenge
the Uchiha Clan.
Afterwards, I learned the truth
from Tobi and Danzo.
その後　トビとダンゾウから
本当のことを聞いた。
そして俺は
木ノ葉への復讐へと走った。
And I leaned towards swearing
vengeance against the Leaf.
だが…　だが
あんたの口から聞いておきたい。
However, I want to hear it
straight from your mouth.
イタチの…　イタチのすべてを。
Everything regarding Itachi.
そうなったか。
So it came to that...
同胞を殺めさせたうえ
逆賊の濡れ衣を着せ→
Not only did I have him
kill his brethren...
I also had him bear
the false charge of traitor...
更には　暁どもを
一人で監視させていた。
and keep tabs on the Akatsuki
all by himself.
イタチは　小さき頃から
誰も気にとめぬ→
From the time he was
a small child,
Itachi paid attention
to the teachings and signs
先人たちからの
教えや印に気づき→
of our predecessors that
no one else gave heed to.
一人で　かつての忍や
里の起こりを感じ取る→
He was a sensitive child
who understood our village's past
and our shinobi.
繊細な子であった。
そのせいか　イタチは　一族という
縛りにとらわれることなく→
And perhaps due to that,
the trappings of a clan
never bound Itachi.
忍の先　里の先について
考えることができ→
He was able to think ahead
about the future
of shinobi and of the village.
いつもそれら将来を危惧していた。
And constantly had misgivings
regarding those futures.
７歳にして　まるで火影のような
考えを持つ少年じゃった。
Even at the age of seven,
he thought like a Hokage.
わしらは
イタチ一人にすべてを任せ→
We left everything to Itachi
in his hands alone...
イタチはそれを
任務として完璧に果たした。
and he executed
his missions perfectly.
同胞を皆　抹殺し　反乱を止め→
He killed his entire clan
and stopped a revolt.
それにつながる戦争を
一人で食い止め→
Prevented a coming war
all by himself.
暁にスパイとして入り込んでまで
里を守った。
He even infiltrated the Akatsuki as
a spy to protect the village.
わしに　お前を里で守ることを
条件に出してな。
On the condition that I protect you
within the village.
やはりそうか。
So it's all true.
（扉間）うちはの呪われた運命
というやつよ。
This is part of
the Uchiha's cursed fate.
壊滅状態だとはな。
I can't believe they're on
the brink of extinction.
クーデターまで企てるに至ったか。
So they even plotted a coup...
いずれそのようなことになると
ふんでおった。
I'd envisioned that it might come
to something like that.
マダラの意志を持つ反乱分子も
くすぶっていたからな。
The rebellious elements bearing
Madara's will had been smoldering.
（大蛇丸）そう
うちはを追い込んだのは→
But you're the one who drove
the Uchiha to it, Lord Second...
二代目。　あなたの作った
うちは警務部に→
It could be said that
the seeds got sown
with the Uchiha Police Force
that you created.
端を発してるとも言えるわ。
なんだと？
What did you say?
犯罪者を取り締まる側は
時として嫌われ者になりやすい。
Those who crack down on crime
tend to be easily disliked.
更にそういう組織は
権限が強い分　思い上がる。
The more authority
such a group has,
the more conceited it can get.
犯罪者を監視させる名目で→
By building the Police Station
next to the prison
警務部を　牢獄と同じ場所に作り→
under the pretext of facilitating
the monitoring of criminals,
うちはの家族を
露骨に里の隅に追いやった。
you conspicuously shoved
the Uchiha Clan
to the margins of the village.
あれが　マダラ分子を助長させたのよ。
That's what fostered
the adherents to Madara.
（柱間）扉間。
あれほど　うちはを→
Tobirama!
Did I not emphasize to you
over and over again
ないがしろにしてはならぬと
念を押しておいただろう。
not to slight the Uchiha?
うちはにこそ出来る役職を与え→
But I gave them positions that
they were eminently qualified for.
次のマダラが出てきたとしても→
And I believed that even if
another Madara were to emerge,
すぐに対処できるよう
考えた結果だ。
he could be dealt with right away.
兄者も知っているだろう。
やつら　うちはは→
As you well know, older brother,
the Uchiha are...
悪に憑かれた一族だ。
...a clan possessed by evil!
（大蛇丸）まるでマダラは
トラウマのようですね。
It's like Madara left
a psychological scar upon you.
そんなに　うちはが怖いと。
To cause such fear of the Uchiha.
（扉間）若僧が。
お前はマダラを知らぬ。
You stripling.
You do not know Madara.
二代目火影　あんたに聞く。
Second Hokage,
a question for you...
うちは一族とは何だ？
何を知ってる。
What is it about the Uchiha Clan?
What do you know?
ふう。
うちは一族と　我ら千手一族は→
The Senju and Uchiha Clans
長きにわたり
戦い続けた歴史がある。
share a long history
of battling each other.
元来その二つの一族は
敵どうしだった。
We were once bitter enemies.
そこは知っている。
I know that already...
悪に憑かれた一族とは
どういう意味だ？
What did you mean about
the Uchiha being possessed by evil?
（扉間）千手一族が術ではなく→
There used to be a thought that
in contrast to the Senju Clan,
愛情を力としているのに対し→
who based their strength in love
as opposed to jutsu...
うちは一族は術の力を
第一とした考えがあった。
The basis of
the Uchiha Clan's strength
was the power of their jutsu.
だが　本当は違うのだ。
However, the truth
is actually different.
うちはほど
愛情に深い一族はいない。
There is no clan that feels
deeper love than the Uchiha.
だからこそ
うちはは　それを封印してきた。
And that is why the Uchiha have
suppressed and sealed it away.
どういうことだ？
What do you mean?!
いったん
うちは一族の者が愛情を知ると→
Once a member of the Uchiha
knows love, it's almost as if
今まで縛りつけてきた
情の解放とでもいうのか→
all of his or her previously
checked emotions are released.
千手をも超える愛の力
というものに目覚めてしまう。
They awaken
a profound love and power
that exceeds even the Senju's.
なら　オーケーじゃん？
But why is that a problem?
千手ともうまくいくでしょ。
It should help things go smoothly
with the Senju too...
その強い愛の力ってので。
This super-strong
power of love, right?
ところが　これが厄介なのだ。
Except it is quite problematic.
強すぎる愛情は
暴走する可能性を秘めていた。
This great power hides within it
the possibility of
going out of control.
愛を知った　うちはの者が→
When an Uchiha who has known
love loses that deep love,
その強い愛情を失ったとき→
it is replaced by an even
stronger hate that changes them.
より強い憎しみに取って代わり→
人が変わってしまう。
わしは　それを何度も見てきた。
I've seen it happen
quite a few times.
そして　それには
ある特別な症状が出るのだ。
And that's when
a special condition emerges.
症状？
Condition?
（扉間）うちはの者が
大きな愛の喪失や→
When an Uchiha writhes
in agony over the loss
自分自身の失意に
もがき苦しむとき→
of a great love or disappointment
in themselves,
脳内に特殊なチャクラが吹き出し→
a unique chakra is released
inside their brain and
視神経に反応して
眼に変化が現れる。
reacts with the optic nerves and
changes appear that person's eyes.
それが　心を写す瞳→
The eyes that reflect the heart.
写輪眼と言われるものだ。
This is what we call the Sharingan.
The Sharingan taps into
the power of that person's heart,
（扉間）写輪眼は　心の力と同調し→
個人を急速に強くさせる。
rapidly increasing their strength,
along with the power of their hate.
心の憎しみの力とともに。
うちはには
確かに繊細な者が多く→
There were many sensitive
individuals among the Uchiha,
強い情に目覚めた者は→
and nearly all who were
exposed to strong emotions
ほぼ闇にとらわれ悪に落ちる。
were taken over by darkness
and fell to evil.
闇が深くなればなるほど→
The deeper the darkness gets
瞳力も増し
手がつけられなくなる。
the greater
the Visual Prowess becomes,
until the person can
no longer be stopped.
マダラのようにな。
Just like Madara.
マダラは　弟思いの男だった。
Madara cared deeply
for his younger brother...
貴様の兄以上だろうぞ。
His love was, perhaps, greater
than your brother's love for you.
（扉間）わしは　うちはの力を
里のために貢献できるように→
I thought I had arranged
and guided things as such
that the Uchiha's power could
be harnessed to serve the village.
形を整え　導いたつもりだ。
だが　里のために
自滅したのだとしたら→
Although if they self-destructed
for the sake of the village,
then so be it.
それも　しかたのないこと。
やつらも木ノ葉の里の
役に立ったということだ。
Either way, in the end, they were
of use to the Leaf Village.
（柱間）扉間！
そういう言い方はよさぬか！
Tobirama! Stop talking like that!
話を聞いているのは
純粋なうちはの子供だ。
You are speaking to
an innocent Uchiha child!
（扉間）大事なのは里だ。　里が要よ。
What is all-important
is the village.
The village is the keystone.
兄者もそれは　わかっていよう。
I know that you know
that too older brother.
気にしない。
It doesn't bother me.
純粋でもなければ
子供でもない。
I am neither innocent nor a child.
《基本巴ではない。
It's not the standard pattern...
万華鏡写輪眼か》
It's the Mangekyo Sharingan...
初代火影　あんたに聞く。
First Hokage... I ask you this...
里とは何だ？
What does it mean to be a village?
忍とは　そもそも何なんだ？
And what does it mean
to be a shinobi?
What is a village,
and what are shinobi?
里　忍とは何ぞ？　か。
イタチは　兄は　木ノ葉に
利用されたにもかかわらず→
My older brother Itachi, despite
having been used by the Leaf,
defended the village with his life.
命がけで里を守り→
He died a proud Leaf Shinobi.
木ノ葉の忍であることに
誇りを抱いて逝った。
同胞を殺してまで→
So what exactly is this village,
己が死んでまで守ろうとする
里とは　いったい何だ？
that one strives to protect even
if it means killing one's kin?
Even if it means their own death?
こんな状況を作り上げた忍→
And what are shinobi who've
created such circumstances
それをよしとする忍とは
何なんだ？
and consider them acceptable?
あんたの言葉を聞いて
本当のことを知ってから→
I'll listen to your response
and find out the truth,
自分で答えを出したい。
and then I'll make my decision...
木ノ葉に復讐をするのか
それとも…。
Whether or not to declare
vengeance against the Leaf.
Or...
((大蛇丸。
何？
Orochimaru...
What is it?
あんたは　木ノ葉を
一度　潰そうとした。
You once tried to
destroy the Leaf...
初めは気まぐれだと言った
あんたの言葉を信じたが→
At first, when you said you
did it on a whim, I believed you.
今は違うとわかる。
But now, I know it was
something different.
(本当は　なんだったんだ？))
What was the real reason?
（扉間）木ノ葉への復讐だと？
Vengeance against the Hidden Leaf?
うちはの悪に憑かれた小僧が。
You brat possessed
with the Uchiha evil!
ここで　わしが！
In that case I shall...
Lord Second!
二代目様。
扉間。
Tobirama!
《か…　貫禄　ハンパねえ！！》
Now we're talking presence!
指をおろせ。
Lower your finger.
All right...
（扉間）わかった…
そうチャクラを荒立てるな　兄者。
Don't get your chakra
so riled up, brother.
ハハハハハ！　いや　すまんすまん。
Sorry about that!
ホッ…。
すごいですね。
Wow, that's incredible!
You haven't changed a bit,
Lord Hashirama...
《相変わらずですの　柱間様》
フン…。
（柱間）しかし　よい兄を持ったな
サスケとやら。
Well then, Sasuke,
you had a good older brother.
俺以上の忍ぞ！
He was a greater shinobi
than I ever was!
里について話してやってもよいが
ちと長くなるぞ。
I don't mind telling you more
about the village,
but it will take a while.
If possible, could you
please tell the child
（大蛇丸）できれば早急に
この子の聞きたいことを→
everything he wants
to know quickly?
話してあげてください。
あまり時間もないので。
We don't have much time.
時間がない？
No time?
今は戦争中です。
うちはマダラが復活し→
We're in the middle of a war.
Madara Uchiha has been revived
この世の忍を
消すつもりのようです。
and apparently intends to erase
all the shinobi of this world.
いつの世も戦いか…。
Always conflict,
no matter what the era.
確かに　ここから　２時の方向…。
I definitely feel
some powerful chakra
何やら強いチャクラを感じる。
in the direction of 2 o'clock.
《ミナト：これは　ナルトと九尾のチャクラ
そうか…。
This is Naruto and
Nine Tails' chakra.
I see
やったんだな　ナルト！
So you did it, Naruto!
そして　一緒に戦っている
今も！》
And you're fighting together...
even now!
ウソではないようだな
確かにマダラのチャクラを感じる。
It seems to be true.
I'm definitely sensing
Madara's chakra.
なら　わしらは戦場へ向かう。
Then we ought to head
to the battlefield.
あなた方は　私の穢土転生の術の
管理下にあり→
As all of you are under the control
of my Reanimation Jutsu,
your movements can be restricted.
その行動は制限される。
戦場へ向かいたいなら
話を済ませてからです。
If you insist,
you may head to the battlefield
after we finish talking.
話はあとじゃ！
マダラが復活したと聞いて→
Talk later!
Do you truly understand
the gravity of Madara
having been revived?
事の重大さがわかっておるのか！？
私は　この子に付きます。
I'm sticking with this child.
サスケ君が納得しなければ
あなたたちを使って→
If Sasuke isn't satisfied
with your explanation,
I may use all of you to destroy
the Leaf now.
ここ　木ノ葉を潰すことに
なりかねませんよ。
このタイミングで。
The timing couldn't be better.
ぬぬぬ…　こんな術！
This jutsu--!
（扉間）大蛇丸とやら
お前　何か勘違いをしておる。
Orochimaru, was it?
You seem to be
misunderstanding something.
前回よりも
穢土転生の術の精度を→
The fact that you've upped
the precision of the Reanimation
上げてしまったことが
あだとなったな。
since the last time shall
be your downfall.
わしらが本来の力に近いまま
この世に転生された今回…。
Now that we've been revived
at close to our original power...
I am not someone who can be bound
貴様ごときの穢土転生に
縛られる　わしではないわ！
by the Reanimation of
one such as you.
そもそも　この術を考案したのは
この　わしよ。
Do not forget,
I am the one who devised
this jutsu in the first place.
兄者　こうなっては致し方ないぞ
わしは動く！
Older brother, you must agree
that we have no choice.
I will take action!
猿飛　かなりの忍を育てたものだ。
Sarutobi, you sure raised
quite a shinobi.
忍の神に褒めていただいて
光栄です。
It is an honor to be praised
by the God of Shinobi himself.
ハハハハハ！　俺の細胞を取り込み
縛る力を上げておるのよ。
He's acquired my cells and
enhanced his power to bind us!
扉間　お前　少し勘が鈍っておるぞ。
Tobirama...
Your instincts have dulled a bit.
《扉間：こやつ…
よくよく感知してみれば→
Damn him...
Taking a closer look,
体のほとんどが
兄者の細胞ではないか》
most of his body is composed
of my older brother's cells...
さて…。
Now then...
《この人は違う…。
First Hokage Hashirama...
初代　火影　柱間…。
He's different.
私の縛りをほどき
いつでも私を…。
He could undo my binding
at any time...
気を抜かぬようにしなければ》
I have to be careful not
to let down my guard.
大蛇丸とやら　心配するな。
Orochimaru... Do not fret.
その子を縛っているわだかまりを
解いてやるほうを先としようぞ。
My priority is to undo
the ill feelings
that are binding this child.
I don't know what he will decide
after he is done listening to me...
（柱間）うちはの子が
俺の話を聞き→
どう選択するかはわからぬが→
この子を今　無視すれば
のち　必ず次のマダラとなろうぞ。
But if we ignore him now,
he will definitely become
the next Madara.
それでは　戦争が終わり
勝ったとしても　意味がないのう。
If that happens, ending the war
and winning will be meaningless.
（扉間）ハァ～　兄者の好きにせい。
Do as you please, older brother.
さて　ではどこから
話すべきかのう。
Now then...
Where should I start?
そうよの…。
Yes...
（柱間）まず　里と忍について
語るには…。
In order to talk to you
about village and shinobi...
((木遁　木龍の術))
Wood Style: Wood Dragon Jutsu!
（柱間）うちはと
千手についてからだのう。
I must first speak of
the Uchiha and Senju Clans...
((木遁　木人の術。
Wood Style!
Wood Golem Jutsu!
獣の難をくらう
木遁　榜排の術か。
The Wood Style Wood
Expulsion Jutsu, was it?
Perfect for taking on
difficult beasts...
ん！？
He clad his Susano'o around
the Tailed Beast like armor!
《尾獣に須佐能乎を鎧として
着させるとはのう。
マダラめ　考えよる》
Madara, you crafty fox!
（柱間）
もう　ぬしの太刀筋は読める。
I can read your sword swings!
木遁　皆布袋の術！
Wood Style:
Laughing Buddha Jutsu!
くっ！
《このままでは　陸が
むちゃくちゃになる。
At this rate, this land
will be completely obliterated.
It's best to move this
to the seashore!
海辺に移動したほうがいい》
（マダラ）逃がさん！
You're not getting away!
うっ！
これでもう　つかむのは無理だぞ。
There, try grabbing that!
（マダラ）どうする？
What will you do now?!
Summoning...
《口寄せ　五重羅生門！》
Five-Layer Rashomon!
《これで…》
This...
《軌道は変えられたか》
will change the trajectory!
向こうの陸まで。
All the way to the other shore?
柱間…　お前と本気でやるのは
久しいからな。
Hashirama...
It's been a while since we've
fought each other earnestly!
昔とは違うのがわかったろ。
You can see that I have changed!
You're going to
lay everything to waste?
（柱間）今までのことを
俺たちの努力を→
To all we've accomplished up
until now, Madara?
無駄にするのか？　マダラ。
俺とお前が戦ったところで
何も生まれん。
Nothing will come of us
battling each other...
この戦いは
里と忍を傷つけるだけだ。
This fight will only hurt
the village and shinobi!
俺たちの兄弟を　仲間を
侮辱するだけだぞ！
This is an insult towards
our siblings and our friends!
お前に　俺の…。
You know nothing of my--!
俺は　お前を殺したくない。
I don't want to kill you!
それは　俺を
いつでも殺せるってことか？
Are you implying that
you could kill me at any time?
違う　俺たちは友だと…。
No! I'm saying we're friends!
俺はもう　届いたのさ！
I've already...reached it!
しかたない…　仙法。
《木遁　真数千手！》
いくぞ　マダラ！
来い！　柱間！
うぉ～！
(うぉ～！))
＜旬の野菜が大好きな豆助＞
≫豆助
きょうのお野菜は
今が旬のアレよ？
＜　その野菜とは？＞